Phyllis Duganne Papers, 1903-1965
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Phyllis Duganne papers
1930-1965
Duganne, Phyllis, 1899-1976
MS 52
9 boxes (6 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Author. Suffragist. Typescripts of Duganne's short stories comprise most of the collection, although there are also typescripts of five novels, a number of plays and scrapbooks. Correspondence with her agent Carl Brandt reflects her attempt to break into the television and film writing industries.
Phyllis Duganne (1899-1976) was born in Boston, descended from a long line of New England farmers and seagoing Cape Codders. She spent summers in Scituate with her aunt, Inez Haynes Irwin. Irwin was a well-known author, suffragist, and feminist, and in Scituate, Duganne was surrounded by artists and writers. Duganne worked in New York City as a short story writer from the 1920s to the 1950s. In 1919, she was one of "nine brilliant members of the Bobbed Hair Brigade of Greenwich Village who borned the buxom young magazine Judy" with Freda Kirchway, Margaret Sangster, and Jane Burr. Judy, which included poems by Duganne's aunt, Inez Haynes Irwin was promoted as a magazine for the modern woman and the men who wished to understand her. Duganne also published in Saturday Evening Post, Ladies Home Journal, Colliers, and other magazines, and she published two novels, one of which was Prologue (1920). Love stories, often tragic, were her specialty. Duganne also wrote for young female readers, including a novel, Ruthie, and short stories for American Girl Magazine. Duganne also had some success as a writer for television and film. Her play Nice Girl was made into a movie in 1941, starring Deanna Durban. Duganne's first marriage was to a writer, Austin Parker. Their daughter Jane was born in 1920. Duganne divorced Parker when he became involved with Broadway actress and film star Miriam Hopkins. Duganne's second marriage was to Eben Given, an artist and author. They lived in Truro, Massachusetts, where Duganne continued to write, garden, and sail.
The bulk of the papers date from the 1920s to the 1940s, when Duganne was most prolific in her short story writing. Typescripts of Duganne's short stories comprise most of the collection, although there are also typescripts of five novels and a number of plays, all arranged alphabeltically when the title could be determined. From the 1920s' on, when Duganne was best known as a short story writer for leading women's magazines, such as Ladies Home Journal, Redbook Magazine, and Colliers, she produced many of the typescripts and related material in this collection. There are four issues of Judy, but little else related to the magazine or the "Bobbed Hair Brigade." Duganne's correspondence with her agent Carl Brandt from the late 1930s on reflects her somewhat successful attempt to break into the television and film writing industries. There are also five oversize scrapbooks, two containing newspaper clippings, and three more of published short stories.
This collection is organized into three series:
I. Biographical Materials
II. Correspondence
III. Writings
Oversize Materials
Books on Shelf
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Additions to the Collection
Additions to collection are expected.
History of the Collection
The Phyllis Duganne Papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1981 by her daughter, Jane Parker.
Search Terms
Duganne, Phyllis, 1899-1976; Cape Cod (Mass.)--History--20th century--Sources; Greenwich Village (New York, N.Y.)--History--20th century--Sources; Authors, American--20th century; Dramatists, American--20th century; Fiction--Authorship--History--20th century--Sources; Women authors, American--20th century; Judy, a magazine (New York, N.Y., 1919)
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - Contents and accession information (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biography: reviews, biographical writings, and photographs (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook: newspaper clippings, 1922
    [See OVERSIZE MATERIALS]
  - Scrapbook (present from Inez Haynes Irwin, Christmas 1903)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Outgoing, 1926, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Incoming
    - 1933-55, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Re: "Terrible Teens" writings, 1934-35 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Professional from Brandt & Brandt, 1937-65 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- SERIES III. WRITINGS
  - Contracts and royalty statements, 1920-77 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Judy, A Magazine (4 issues), 1919 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Novels
    - Going to the Sun: typescripts, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - The House of Susanna: typescripts, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - No cover charge: typescripts, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Prologue: correspondence and reviews,1920 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      [See BOOKS ON SHELF for published copy]
    - The Touchstone: typescripts, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Plays: typescripts, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Short Stories: typescripts, undated
    - A-C (Box 2, Folder 2-4)
    - D (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - The "Dody" Stories (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - E-H (Box 3, Folder 3-6)
    - I-L (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    - The "Leo" Stories (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - M-O (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
    - P-V (Box 5, Folder 1-5)
    - W-Z (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    - Unfinished: notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous published stories, 1921-61 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous
    - The Writer, Jul 1957, Apr 1963 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Bare Island [notes for unfinished novel?] (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Writings by Jane Parker, and Edith and Samuel Grafton, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Scrapbooks of published short stories (3), 1923-31
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Scrapbooks
    - Recipes, essays, and anecdotes: newspaper clippings, 1922 (Box 7)
    - Gift from Inez Hayes Irwin, Christmas: magazine pictures with captions by Irwin, 1903 (Box 7)
    - Stories
      - 1923-26 (Box 8)
      - 1927-30 (Box 8)
      - 1931 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous stories (1 folder)
- BOOKS ON SHELF
  - Prologue, by Phyllis Duganne